# Jacob Z. Eliason

jacobeliason@gmail.com

github.com/jcblsn | linkedin.com/in/jacobzeliason | jacobeliason.com

Based in Washington, DC, USA US Govt Clearance Level: Secret

#### SUMMARY

I'm a data scientist with a background in Bayesian statistics and causal inference and recent experience with generative Al. During my graduate studies in 2023 I pursued coursework in deep learning and cloud computing to complement my background in traditional statistics. In my current role, I've developed Python-based automation tools in Azure Cloud following Agile development practices, demonstrating my ability to write production-grade code in a mature environment.

#### **EDUCATION**

### The London School of Economics and Political Science

M.Sc. Statistics

London, United Kingdom Sep 2022 – Aug 2023

- Relevant coursework: Statistical Inference, Generalized Linear Modeling, Bayesian Machine Learning, Distributed Computing (used GCP), Deep Learning (used TensorFlow)
- Project: Comparing Deep Learning Approaches to Image Segmentation for Deforestation Detection
  - Developed and evaluated deep learning models using Python and TensorFlow for segmenting satellite images
- Dissertation: Estimating the Causal Effect of German Nuclear Plant Closures on Electricity Generation Using Gaussian Process Regression
  - Employed causal inference methodologies and Bayesian machine learning modeling techniques to analyze energy data

# **Brigham Young University**

**B.S. Statistics** 

Provo, UT, United States Jan 2016 – Dec 2019

- Minors: Mathematics, Political Science
- · Relevant coursework: Intro to Bayesian Statistics, Applied Bayesian Statistics, Analyis of Correlated Data

#### **EXPERIENCE**

<u>Guidehouse</u>

Data Scientist - Senior Consultant

Arlington, VA, USA Aug 2023 – Present

- Developed, deployed, and maintained the backend of a reporting tool for a US Department of State client in Python using Azure Cloud used by several hundred employees, following Agile development practices
- Contributed research to improve the factual accuracy of internal LLM tooling using LangChain and chain-of-verification prompting
- Used Python, Azure

# DevTech Systems, Inc.

Statistician

Arlington, VA, USA Feb 2022 – Aug 2022

Wrote R code to apply statistical disclosure limitation methods with sdcMicro to agency data assets to satisfy k-anonymity and reduce risk

# **United States Census Bureau**

Mathematical Statistician

Washington, DC, USA Sep 2020 – Feb 2022

- Wrote and edited programs in SAS using SQL for production work on the <u>Survey of Income and Program Participation</u>; responsibilities included sampling, weighting, and variance estimation
- · Used SAS, SQL, R

# **Y2 Analytics**

Data Analyst

Salt Lake City, UT, USA Jan 2020 – Aug 2020

- Contributed to elections modeling effort by modeling education and turnout using hierarchical Bayesian model
- Conducted survey research projects for <u>corporate and municipal government clients</u> from start to finish: programmed questionnaires in Qualtrics, cleaned survey data using y2clerk, produced graphics using ggplot2, analyzed relationships using conjoint analysis and other statistical modeling tools, and wrote text for final deliverables

Data Analyst Intern

Washington, DC, USA May 2019 – Aug 2019

. Wrote new functions and corresponding unit tests for in-house R package which are still used years later by 10+ analysts

#### **SKILLS**

- Programming
  - Languages: Python, R, SQL, Stan
  - Version Control, Testing
  - o Cloud: Azure, GCP
  - o Scripting: Unix Shell
- Data Management & Engineering
  - Big Data: Databricks, PySpark
  - Pipeline Orchestration: Dagster, Airflow
- Artificial Intelligence & Deep Learning

- Frameworks: TensorFlow, PyTorch
- o Architectures: CNN, RNN, transformer
- o Tooling: LangChain
- Statistical Analysis & Machine Learning
  - Theory: Probability and inference, hypothesis testing, Bayesian methods, linear and non-linear modeling
  - Application: generalized linear models, time series, causal inference, supervised & unsupervised ML